hello and welcome this is active guest
stream 47.1 on July 10 2023 we're here
with Nick bird and Samuel Bellini lychee
and we're going to have a presentation
followed by a discussion so thank you
both for joining and Sam thanks again
for this presentation off to you
let's see uh was Nick gonna say
something before I started
oh I can go ahead okay
okay uh so some introduction first I'm a
professor Minister State University
I'm a psychologist philosopher mainly
working in cognitive science I'm going
to talk about what I did in my DHC
thesis
and
also some renewed interests I had on
this based on some developments in large
large language models which happened
this year uh most notably chain of
thoughts and tree of thoughts
those additions to Varnish language
model made me want to come back to this
again and talk to this talk about this
so how do you know about human reasoning
which is the subject the main subject
underlying this topic
well we had Empirical research from the
60s starting with Peter Watson who was
challenging the notion that we have a
logic
logical models for reasoning or some
general understanding of understanding
of logic when we're adults
and he crafted tasks which were
hard to to solve but they had actually
simple fundamentals to it
uh which shows which we're taking to
scene taken to show
people's irrationality and something
like that and also a
huge tradition that's called Logistics
and biases and also started in the 60s
and the 70s
mainly by continent and almost first
king
which had similar tasks and went beyond
and they even won the the Nobel Prize
for this work
yeah I I had here in the slides
evolutionary psychology and language and
pragmatics which were also
people in the 90s working with this sort
of research but I'm gonna talk about
dual process Theory
uh in the way they are formulated by
Evans and stanovic
which uh
mainly
summarizes the results of Watson and and
[Music]
so I'm going to talk about how do
process Theory came to be and then some
problems that it has that I try to
address
so one of the first first reasoning
tasks in in this Trends or literature
was the Watson selection test which goes
like this please indicate each cards can
determine if the following rule is false
if the card has a vowel on one side then
has an even number on the other side
um
this sounds like a simple exercise so
the card a clearly is relevant because
it has a problem on one side which is if
it doesn't have an even number on the
other then
the statement is false and everyone can
can find this neatly of most people
but the problem comes with the the card
seven which
is not so intuitive people actually
choose the second the second
cartoon there which has an even number
on one side but having that even number
doesn't help at all
to determine if the statement is false
what does help is
which is an odd number if it has a vowel
on the other side then the statement
could be
so
this was one of the tasks that
was famous for
and
University
children
this one they're famous task as well
it's called the consumption 2000 the
issue that people
derive and solve this sense
it is uh because it goes like this it is
a 31 years old single outspoken and very
bright she majored in philosophy as a
student she was deeply concerned with
issues of discrimination and social
justice and also participated in
anti-nuclear demonstrations please make
the following statements by their
probability is important for the most
probable and eight for these problems
uh
what's interesting here is the
disease statement the last statement
Linda is a bank teller and it is an
active
is active in the feminist movement
because there's also
there are also these statements without
one another without the conjunction
which is active in the famous movement
and then there is a bank account
because of the description people think
there's a feminist is is very likely
given the description
but they think being a bank teller is
not likely
the issue is that people uh usually
marks Linda is a bank teller and is a
feminist as more likely than being the
main seller
the problem here is that the conjunction
of the two necessarily is less likely
so being a famous plus being something
else or being a bank Target plus being
something else is automatically less
likely
um
so those are the sort of tasks that
the reasoning literature used to show
some sort of human irrationality
uh one issue with this is that
very interesting to show
that humans are irrational it's more
interesting to show how we how humans
reason
and also
these sort of studies didn't show how
people actually
solved the the Departments they were
actually focused on how people made
mistakes
uh one thing that's interesting about
dual process theory is that explains
both the mistakes and the solutions to
to the answers
so in 2002 Carmen and Frederick
formulated this cognitive reflection
task which is another one of these tasks
but it's a lot more simpler and elegant
and it really shows
indicates at least how dual process
theory is a good solution to a good
explanation of the evidence in general
so
yeah the Western selection test used
logic in
and
the Linda task use probability and here
we just have basic arithmetics so basic
math you don't have to to worry about
which which answer is truly correct or
which rational Norms we need to follow
it's just basic management it's
there's nothing to discuss here right so
the test goes like this
a bat involved costs one in ten in total
you might know this as it's a famous
sense even out of the reasoning
literature the back costs one more than
well how much does the ball cost
so people when when people read this
they usually say 10 cents intuitively
but if you take a little time to write
write it down you can see that it's
actually five cents so uh
the bats
costs one and five cents and the ball
costs five cents together and it costs
one insane
uh the other two have a similar
structure the point here is that
sometimes we
look at these tasks and we have an
intuitive answer
which is wrong
and the way we get get out of these
these issues
is that you stop and think a little bit
and review our answers with some sort of
step-by-step reasoning so writing it
down something like that
uh what's interesting here is like if
you look at two plus two
it's almost impossible not to think four
it's just it's almost like you're
perceiving the answer is four just by
looking at it but if you have some sort
of more complex calculation to do
obviously just by looking at it you
won't have a solution
so this basic uh intuition is clearly
shown in the cognitive reflection task
and what's more interesting about it is
that the cognitive reflection test
actually predicts the performance of
various emissions and biases tasks so if
someone does well on the cognitive
reflection test they're more likely to
go well on any other reasoning task
uh and if they go
bad on the cognitive transaction test
that you'd like to go back on other
resume tests as well this is also to me
this is also
an indication that this dual process
structure of intuitive reasoning versus
slow reasoning reflective reasoning
likely explains the rest of the tests as
well not only do you sue but most of the
others so it's a good explanation of the
literature
okay so what does the theory say
uh decides besides explaining
the
the reasoning literature
so in 2008 Jonathan Evans tried to make
a formulation of it that would include
uh
and unified views from different
different domains such as social
cognition neurosciences
uh other people in psychologists we had
which had similar theories and it seems
like there's something in
in
uh important here to unified but Evans
wasn't able to and so
there's a formulation specific for
reasoning and we don't know if it
applies so much well to to other areas
of technician
well one common way
to describe dual process theory is by
making these tables of features so we
say oh type 1 processes have these sorts
of features on the left in type 2
processes like this other type of
features on the right
uh this table here was one I made by
joining some of the features of Evans
and stanovich and also of Kahneman
and then with some questions
I raised in the thesis I elaborated it
this way but it's very similar to the
events and standard HTML formulation
one problem we have with this
tables
formulation of the developed process
theory is that usually people agree that
in one thinking instance when you're
solving a problem you're not going to
have all of those features together
so we don't know for sure
when some feature will be president not
for instance so clear that type 1
processes necessarily have to be under
conscious and type 2 processes
necessarily have to be conscious
uh I think that comes a lot because of
some conceptual issues in in the theory
but one solution they have found was to
have at least some defining features
but different authors have different
defining features so here I have some of
the defining features of the the main
authors
which is type 1 processes use less
working memory
uh once had two processes loads strongly
on working memory
type one processes part autonomous in
this sense that they don't need to wait
for higher processing to respond if they
have an answer they go for it and using
the couple's representations mean that
means that type 2 systems can
reason Beyond what's what's in the
present environment you can
think about things that are not there
uh tech one processing is faster in
comparison R2 is lower in comparison
type 1 processing
is less effortful
well two is more ethical in the sense of
psychological effort effort like people
reports having a hard time doing things
so
for instance in the cognitive reflection
test
people that solved the test correctly
usually rate it is harder
because they had to use
the type 2 processing to solve it
okay but Samuels which is a philosopher
a dual process theory in other subjects
he says okay even if these features
proposal is good you see we still need a
mechanism to explain
why these features are linked together
so
what what is the mechanism that explains
why type 1 processing features go
together
and what is the mechanism that explains
why type two
processing
goes together so we need some
Beyond saying that they're different you
need to explain
what are these mechanisms that make them
differ
and I actually had Samuels online
uh
PhD committee and I'm not sure if he was
convinced with my solution so my PhD was
a solution to this problem I'm not sure
how how he was convinced of it
but he approved the the PHD so that's
good enough I guess
um
yeah the way I
so the goal was to solve the unity
problem is to explain the mechanisms
that that explain type 1 processing and
explain the mechanisms to explain type 2
processing
and I started to see to search in the
literature first how people were
conceiving of the general Frameworks
that were behind these two types of
reasoning
and what that was not actually related
to this literature of dual process
Theory but was actually famous in
cognitive science was the modularity of
mind uh in the 80s it was my first for
General folder and he said that uh
we had two
types of gross and cities the modular
process mostly related to input and
perception
then we had Central processes that was
mostly related to higher reasoning so
you can
Trace some sort of resemblance there to
do process Theory
and the way he went about this is that
he said
these perceptual models the modular
processes are information encapsulating
so Vision only works with vision and
language only works with language space
when it goes to space
and so these were domain-specific
knowledge systems that did not
communicate with each other
uh
and when they needed contact sensitivity
they needed Central processes so these
Central processes he would argue were
isotropic and finance which means that
any
type of information could be used in a
solution so we can relate I don't know
physics with Biology and form a new
solution so there's Knowledge from
multiple domains working here and that
that which they would also need some
sort of context sensitivity sensitivity
which was a problem for photo if you
didn't think we would solve this context
sensitivity problem at all
and he had good reasons for that in
classic AI we had
a lot of issues with that I mean you
still do have issues with the consensus
context sensitivity problem
but not uh the sort of issues we had in
the 80s when they were debating this
same problem of classical AI so this
problem was a problem with how to
represent a changing environment in
symbolic representation
uh so yeah it was a problem because
classical AI attempted to give knowledge
to robots so
artificial intelligence and statements
about the world and they were
uh
far intractable hard to compute there
are so many knowledge events to search
in so many knowledge to to
try to use the the robots couldn't do
anything relevant
uh they also couldn't representate them
represent a change so the changing
environment was
terrible for them didn't work with this
symbolic representation it didn't work
with serial reasoning or anything like
of the sorts so this was a huge problem
for plastic cognitive scientists
and since photo was a
believer in cognitive science in the
sense of classical computational theory
of mind or language of thought
Theory
she said that
he had found for his first law of the
non-existence of cognitive science this
law states that the more processes are
Global the less cognitive science will
be able to understand them
so he thought only these encapsulated
processes could be studied and if we
needed this sort of global and contact
senses context sensitive
cyber processing then contest science
just can do it
because he had in mind going to science
in the sense of the classical AI
uh
but it also seems not only folder it
seems like the literature abandoned
classical
cognitive science
in various ways which were strange
because if you take the work of Alan new
and Herbert Simon it's strange to think
that oh they were completely wrong
there's nothing nothing useful that they
they say that could be applied today
all the evidence of the theories they
made
but just completely wrong
that's that's a real weird way of
thinking and
well if you take for instance our
theories today of the human Beijing
brain
they don't consider this at all so
it's just like they they don't get a
different strand
theories but it also it always seems to
me that there must be at least something
wrong about uh something right about
this
shouldn't be totally abandoned there
must be a place
for these results
in this explanation of the Mind
one thing that was in arts with the way
forwarder described
this dual process Theory and also
sometimes
stand of age when he talks about dual
process Theory
it seems like it is forgetting this fact
here
is the fact that we have a limited
capacity
um
when we use conscious processing or
working memory
and this is one of the best evidence in
Psychology we have so far
we've had behaviorists evidence for
reinforcement and enforcement learning
and that stuff and then we had cognitive
psychology in the 60 and this is the
best evidence that cognitive psychology
has had for a long time so this is also
something we should not
simply ignore
so we have in short-term memory
the knowledge that
when we store some information in
short-term memory we usually can only
keep track of about seven items
sometimes even less
in selective attention there was this
task
where
there were there was a video of people
playing basketball
and
the subjects had to count how many
passes they were
making and suddenly a gorilla passed by
on the scene and people didn't notice
the gorilla
because they were so concentrated on the
task
which which is some evidence of
selective attention that is when you're
concentrated on the task you actually
don't even see
other interestingly
um
we have also a competition for limited
resources when doing dual tasks or if
I'm talking on the phone and writing at
the same time I'm probably not going to
do a very good writing because we're
competing for a limited resources and
it's important to note that if you're
walking in in riding and walking and
talking so those are different tasks
they won't compete so we had some
competition
we have more more competition when these
limited resources are disputed
also in working memory so if I say the
number seven nine three two four one and
I ask you to repeat them backwards and
you're not looking at the slides you're
going to have a hard time with that
because of the limited capacity is worth
memory when it's clear that
in other areas or thinking of our our
base using a lot more information in
certain items
to to make the scenes happen and
perception and to make us walk and so on
so that's on the side of the type two
constraints on the side of type one
reasoning so common are already has some
intuitions similar to the ones I
described so he said performance
earlier's day days the research that
diversity and I conducted was Guided by
the idea that intuitive judgment Supply
position between the automatic
corporations of perception and the
deliberate operations of reasoning
Carmen and Frederick claimed that
intuitive thinking is perception like
that intuitive predictions is an
operation of system one further that the
boundary between perception and judgment
is fuzzy and permeable the perception of
a stranger as medicine is inseparable
from the prediction of future harm
so you can see that this is very likely
and it's very similar sorry to the
intuitions that we're speaking on when
we're talking about prediction
processing so kind of saying when you
look at a face of someone and he's mad
uh you have a prediction that
you're in trouble right
so this is a sort of judgment that seems
for perception since front reception
also the concept the contact sensitivity
is
pretty much salt in the predictive
processing and if you take on the
AI literature that's also happened for
instance in the paper attention is all
you need they have some
uh tips for how to deal with context
sensitivity which disorder didn't dream
of so this is something that Clark said
in 2013. the best overall fit between
driving signal and expectations will
often be found by in effect inferring
noise in the driving signal and does
recognizing a stimulus as for example
the letter m
saying the context of the word mother
even though the same Bears was presented
out of context or in most other contexts
would have been a better fit with the
letter n
a unit normally responsive to the letter
M might under search circumstances be
successfully driven by and and like
stimulus so what this Clark is trying to
say here that since we have we
represents
using probability
then if the contest says we should go
left to go left if the context says we
should go right we do right because the
representation is
fluid and it accepts
changes really quickly
so that's something that's changed from
the predictive processing architecture
um
but one issue I think that we might see
in the predictive
processing architecture is the lack of
compositionality so symbolic
representations exhibit
compositionalities
meaning that complex representations are
built by combining simpler elements
according to rules or syntax
the meaning of a complex representation
is derived from the meanings of its
constituent Parts the way they are
combined this property allows for the
generation of new and meaningful
Expressions by manipulating simple
instructions so solar in 88 execution
argue that
even as connectionless models succeed
they would likely have some sort of
stimulation of the language of thoughts
that exhibits conversationality in order
to work like we do and you see that
it seemed like it's the case with the
results we have
this year
uh so considering those constraints
and the initial view of order and the
problem I was trying to solve which is
the unity problem from Blue process d
uh
a major shift I had on the PHD thesis
and then I wrote
a chapter on this book which handbook
and found in rationality with Keith
so we
explained here in this book The the
chapter in this this shift the power
structure
which is I mean it's not clear that you
know a dual process theory is theories
would adopt folder but it's still very
similar uh
the way the received field of dual
process Theory Works which is well type
one is a number of dumb heuristics blind
modules and animal intelligence
and then type 2 is the real contextual
and complex reasoning the real human
intelligence so I tried to invert that
power structure by by saying that the
contextual predictive processing
is is a type one reason which which is
giving us
the basics to reason on so our reasoning
already comes with context we don't need
to reason the context with type 2
reasoning
uh we all use type 2 reasoning to fix
some minor issues in predictive
processing when we use heuristic
searching because it's limited uh we
only use it when there's a lot of
prediction error in predictions aren't
working that well
and then we call for this heuristic
search to handle
whatever is missing to see if we can
find a new solution that wasn't captured
so in this case
the powerful system is a predictive
processing and not the the type 2 usage
search right
so that was the general idea for this
shift that now I'm gonna say some
hypothesis
that stems from this shift so T1
processes deal with content encoded in
the form of probability density
functions which is how predictive
processing uses to represent the world
which means there is no symbol and no
definite content those values means the
standard deviation Muslims by previous
movements in the previous World
contingencies
manipulating prior information
biases the distribution into one or
another Direction closer to or further
from a certain value so
people here in the active Insurance
Institute who know this by heart I'm not
changing anything here I'm just using
what they say basically
these functions are not stored in the
memory bank but distributed from the
responsible brain regions over to the
external organs and body parts to neural
connections
the values in the distribution do not
represent objects directly in discreetly
they refer to distance X aspects of the
input when perceptual systems are
dealing with such objects this is in
line with the T1 processes being easily
biased when working with references to
similar properties
like similar numbers objects Rhymes or
pet names very often and the incorrect
value is picked from a distribution an
example that I have from this is when
usually I have seen people confuse their
youngest child with their dog the dark
knee with the youngest child and when
someone has a another new child then the
the youngest the new youngest child is
often confused with the dog because they
are
I think somewhat
represented in singular distributions
significant to the distribution
this is also the language claimers of
embodied proposals that the world is not
represented in synthesis
T1 processes are super personal and
their predictions are made by the same
systems which we process perception a
clear example is that a judgment about a
facial expression is related to the FFA
which is a region we bring that
processes faces and this is also related
to that judgment that continent
[Music]
judgments about their face
the idea is that perception is not
passive but already comes with
predictions and when in problem solving
such prediction is precisely the type 1
answer so if we look back at the the
reasoning tasks all those type 1 tasks
are likely
stemming from predictions
I don't know what to claim that you want
processes are purely perceptual using
consensus superlative only that such
prediction is staying for your
perceptual processes so
what is perception and
currencies I think the word you just
using different words for this is the
problem so just not not getting into
that
convinced example of judgments of
negative spacious Expressions how this
is expected this new process Theory like
uh it's expected of dual process Theory
the type one reason Works under
predictive processing yeah
also in line with the claims of your
body cognition that there is no sharp
link between perception and reasoning
on the other hand C2 processing works
like a classical machine for reasoning
such as general Problem Solver of Newman
Simon
part of this classical machine only made
sense in the brain if it's if it exists
in a wider setup it's predictive
processing Network generating type 1
responses
liking news physical symbol system when
facing reasoning problem T2 processing
opens a problem space containing an
expression the designates the initial
problem
and an expression designates the
solution which was positioned was
productive produced by probabilistic
prediction
having the initial expression in the
predictive expression in the problem
space C2 processing then uses its smooth
generators to attend to reduce
differences between them and sometimes
find different solutions and such bad so
let me just explain this a little bit
better
when neuro was working in the 60s there
they they knew they couldn't search all
possible space of a proper space because
it wouldn't work
so they have this have this search which
works like the detectives
Let's ignore the problems which are
likely wrong and just look at the spaces
that might be right right
uh what this
predicting in reflection framework does
for a music search is that the risk of
search only works on
it works already with the prediction
that was estimated from type bone
processing so it's like we only start
reasoning and making searches
based on
the prior predictions we already had
right and we all we only go
further with the search and the
predictions aren't working
and the main point here
is that the recent search isn't
searching a random space
or even a
pre-programmed space is searching a
space that was left out from the
predictions that started in the type 1
processing so that's how it doesn't go
to the frame problem anymore
because
a large part of the contextual issue was
also already solved by predictive
processes
Okay so
that was the General hypothesis I
presented to attempt to solve the unity
problem which is the problem of how type
1 features go together and how tattoo
features were getting
and now I'm going to try to argue that
this is likely the case
since that I can prove this is the case
but there are good reasons for us to to
think that type 1 processes are
use predictive processing and that types
of processes do not use predictive
processing rather they need some some
kind of symbolic heuristic search
one thing that's that
stands out of is is a good explanation
for the difference between implicit
representation in explicit
representation if you look at the
literature in psychology
you will see that
it's very ambiguous in this these
definitions like people use implicit and
explicit representations as the same
thing as unconscious conscious or
fleeting graphical or the same thing as
automatic in control and so when it goes
to dual process Theory
it's not very clear but they're saying
in which case but they use this
expression implicit and explicit a lot
uh
how I think this model solves this is
by saying that implicit representations
are probability density functions while
explicit representations are symbolic
representations classical symbolic
symbolic representations
uh Clark
in his book sometimes mentions that we
can have single Peak distribution
distributions but the problem with
having single Peak distributions is that
well if you only have one Peak on the
solutions function then it's nice it
doesn't have all these these features of
the probabilistic representation
it's more likely similar to a
symbolic representation in fact that's
having a single Peak distribution might
be the way that
the
probability representation
Ally symbolic representation
so
these have different and important
features so
the probability representation is
continuous
it's uncertain and ambiguous and that's
why it's able to be sensitive to context
a new example the mother example of
choir
it can vary on retrieval we can remember
something and be different in the second
time
uh it's tied to priors it works with
statistical relations
yeah it's it's called in and
depending on which value is most
probable at the time it has a different
outcome right so
I argue that explicit representations
are likely discrete and there are likely
symbolic in nature
they're unambiguous this is what allows
us to disappear in the first place
they're stored reliably if you have a
reliable definition of it you likely
remember it
the same way in the next sign uh it's
arbitrary in the sense that it's not
really coupled to the stingler in the
steam line in the sense that the
perception
of perception usually is the statistical
relations are related to aspects of the
world
uh it's using compositionality and it's
immutable in the sense that you can
change the you can't change it it's
fixed
[Music]
this value doesn't change
so that's the implicit versus explicit
feature you can have also explanations
for ultimaticity contrast to working
memory so automaticity concerns
overlearned skills and Overland skills
are understood as skills that have
become predictable in this framework
here
so you usually use this to explain like
driving riding bicycle riding
um so when you're driving
if you don't know how to drive you need
certain statements like uh
some statements about how you how you
shoot steer right you need to have those
in mind
but then once you learn how to drive
it's like your body uh already knows
what it's doing and you don't even need
to think about this so this is the
classical distinction in Psychology but
I argue that the predictive processing
Theory makes a new
uh
enlightening to this
so it's like our body is predicting what
we're doing so it's automatic so it's an
explanation for ultimate CC but say that
a dog certainly uh suddenly runs
from his car you obviously obviously
don't have a model for that so you're
gonna need to call in working memory to
solve some of those issues and so you
don't hit the dog
so everything works under prediction
unless
the models very unreliable and then
working memory is called in to solve
some
further issues
an interesting hypothesis I had on the
PHD thesis which I never explored and I
actually don't even think anyone read
this part
uh
but it seems to me to be a very
interesting
uh
hypothesis in relation to free energy
and active infants so that's why I'm
bringing it here in the active influence
Institute that as we know the brain
attempts to minimize free energy by
getting predictions right
thus higher need of type 2 processes are
related to Higher free energy
interviewing information in the sense
that
when the predictions are working clearly
then you don't need to
to have effort
but when there are a lot of prediction
error
then you need effort because you'll call
in the working memory to do a risk surge
so to minimize a great amount better
amount of free energy will take more
time in work this is more effort flow
than having predictions ready the
minimize free energy as quickly as
possible before when probabilities fail
the system needs to service game
possibilities
it searches for other possible solutions
by means of heuristic surge
the reset search would be related to
more information and time because it
does not have probable Solutions right
instead it needs to investigate its
state space almost from scratch we say
almost because it is illustrating hence
it also will have tricks to get the
correct solution faster unlike Brute
Force search which would investigate the
state space from beginning to end we
believe reports of effort will be
related to executing more risk searches
there's reports of effort by subjects
would seem to be based on cognitive
information and physical constraints of
reality so that's why I think this is an
interesting part of the hypothesis
is because
we have this psychological measure of
effort but if this is true then we
actually have a physical measure of
efforts like if people are working hard
on a problem that means there's a lot of
free energy going on and they are having
to use
this heuristic search to fix some issues
that the model isn't able to switch by
itself
foreign
yeah so that's that's the effort part so
now going for the working name report
what's interesting here is that
um in working memory
which memory it's like it's it's
expected of it that's that it works like
a classical computer
so
working memory is widely researched
Topic in technology but in predictive
processing it's readily rarely mentioned
and I actually searched the predictive
process in the books it's Ctrl F it's
working memory and people
rarely use this this topic
because
it's not done by predictive processing
it has nothing to do which produce this
processing and it's actually an issue
for predictive processing
because well if you're gonna eliminate
classical symbolic processing all
together then we need a predictive
processing explanation Authority memory
and so far I haven't found one
and I don't think there will be one but
this also could be just ignorance of
mine maybe there's some paper there
which I hadn't found okay
wrong but in any way
uh
working memory
is very aligned with
what touring was thinking when he was
making the the connection between
machines and mines
so if this is a sentence of Alan Turing
explaining
the
his computer right
the turing machine
and if you change the word computer to
working memory it clearly works it's
almost like it's talking about the same
thing when of course if we change the
word here computer to predictive
processing it's clearly you're not
talking about the same thing so the
behavior of the computer or working
memory at any moment is determined by
the symbols which it's observing in his
state of mind that moment we may suppose
that there is a bound B to the number of
symbols of squares which the computer
can observe at one moment if he wishes
to observe more humans use successive
observations
we will also suppose that the number of
states of mind which can be taken into
account is finance
the reason for this are the same
characters as those which restrict the
numbers of symbols
if we admitted an Infinity of states of
mind some of them would be arbitrarily
closed and would be confused again the
Restriction is not one which is
seriously effective computation since
the use of more complicated states of
mind can be resorted by writing more
symbols on the same
so this is very similar to what we think
about when we're talking about working
there not only because we were inspiring
but because of the evidence that
concerned working memory is very similar
to what suspected of this sort of
machine
now finally we have speed so predictive
processing has basically various
strategies to
make the the processing B is faster as
fast as possible while that's not true
for
symbolic classical AI
um
so yeah Clark says cheap fast won't
exploring action rather than the pursuit
of Truth optionality deductive inference
is now the key organizing principle and
he's talking about predictive processing
uh the predictive processor is always
taking certain bets about what the
current state that we were implies
losing accuracy in compensation for
Speed
we also have a predictive coding in the
the more strict sense
so when predictive quality we mean
specifically the property of this system
to consider from the world only
stimulant which result in Greater
prediction error so there's also a
filter there which allows for Speed and
perception
and focusing on predictive prediction
relevance system that only domestic
agents who quickly decide forces of
action and select the moves to amongst
the possible sources
so predictive processing
is sailored to be fast necessarily well
that's not the case for symbolic Ai and
so that's that's the explanation for the
difference in speed so
beyond that the two processes need to
figure out the solutions online so it's
different if you have a prior prediction
that would say to you what the answer is
from having to search a space from from
scratch right there's also another issue
that the biological brains certainly
were not built for a Serial optimistic
search
and so the Republicans say that the
models that the absolute speed of a
process is a property or Excellence of
its implementation in sensitively brain
does not have a symbolic processor
implemented if we do use some sort of
heuristic search it's like a um a
different adaptation it's not it's not
what the brain is is used to the
insertion problem spaces is slower than
having a problem outcome ready with the
stimulates
okay so that was the work I did in um my
PhD thesis and
those one those were one of the main
reasons why I think
these framework is good for explaining
the differences in features of dual
process Theory
and I actually wrote a prediction that I
I just I I recently
learned that I wrote this because I I
forgot I wrote this and then I went back
to to the thesis and then I said well I
actually said this would happen and and
it kind of did so that was one of the
reasons why I I renewed my my interest
in my PhD thesis
so what I said was predictive processing
system would be subject to bias from
lack of compositionalities such as
mistakes and creativity failures and
noticing necessary character from rules
and so on precisely the type of mistake
type 1 processing encouraging so at that
point we didn't have large language
models affecting uh
attention is all you need paper came out
in the same year
and and then I noticed that this could
be seen as a prediction of the type of
issues that large language models are
facing that's we out reliability
part-time keeping the order of units or
steps in complex reasoning or maths
trade
our time letting go of priors and to my
uh
what really motivated me to to start
working at this again was that they
solved this precisely by using dual
process theory in T2 agents that are
calling
so what they're doing now to solve these
reliability issues is adding a heuristic
search to the genitive models and and
it's it's having awesome results this is
just this year it's in 2023
so
the more they develop these type 2
agents to answer these
reliability problems of
large language models the more the large
language models are getting good in that
stuff
so this is this is a paper I got
this is the images from the paper tree
of thoughts right this one which is one
of the last ones
probably came out of them about two
months ago something like that the way
they're they're doing this
implementation is they're taking the uh
the the
um results the outputs of the large
language model and they're doing further
reasoning on it
and then feeding the the large language
model with the result of the further
reasoning the further reason they're
they're doing is very similar to the
classic symbolic AI
so here they explained there's a simple
input output prompting here which is
simply inputting a prompt and the large
language model will give you an output
and as we know these these outputs
sometimes are very biased there's
hallucination on it they're not reliable
you know all of that stuff
and last year they figured out that
through chain of from chain of fat
protein we can also already increase
the reliability of this these models so
you give an input and just as we do the
better prompting you know when we go to
channel and say I'll do this better fix
this issue solve this step by step in
some of the the commands that are good
for chapter
and Chain of Thought protein
automated some of that
some of those reasoning steps and then
large language models were
working much better enough to this so
this was last year and then
last year this started a new trend of
research to to make these agents coupled
to a large language model outputs
[Music]
the large language models to see
how they can get better
um the self-consistency one you give the
input and then there are various
Solutions
the
the self-consistent the sales
consistency forces the large language
model to try different solutions and
then
you get a majority vote so
if you have like five similar answers in
in some different paths
then this one Speaks Over the one which
is less popular
and the tree of thoughts which I thought
was most similar to the the proposals
that I had in in psychology
is the one which opens up the problem
space is it's actually pretty much what
what I just explained in the places I
want to open up a problem space and they
start to search
um
possible solutions which are better than
the original
and they feed that back into the uh
predictive processing oh sorry the
alternative model the large language
model
and then
this this one is uh usually it's
currently one of the best ones yeah
uh so here I made a general
diagram of how this would work
it's not psychology nor AI it's like
what's what's similar in the two
so we have a genitive model here using
probability density functions
this looks more like a traditional
qualitative
connection is model than a predictive
processing Point that's just it's just
the diagram it's not that good I'll talk
a little bit about that
and then
so yeah we generate an answer here which
is to the problem here
and we can get a linguistic output and
this linguistic output then goes for an
heuristic search using symbolic
representations
yeah so if you get a better answer he
repeats it back to the generative model
and so on
basically the knowledge part is the
genitive model and the illusive search
is simply using
more steps to see to prop it back it's
more like a prompting scheme than a new
knowledge scheme which is
both true for the Dual process theory
model I created
and the the heuristic search that's
that's happening here on the t2 agents
for LMS
a better way to do this and I think
we'll start those implementing this is
that the input layers are trying to
predict the thoughts right it's a bit
more like predictive process in the
other diagram
and so they're trying to predict the
thoughts and by opening up this and
searching this problem space during
these
these steps
we already have new new prompts here for
the general model
uh
so if you take predictive processing
seriously then this does happen in the
brain is more likely like this
I do think that the tree of thoughts
paper does say that the intermediary
process isn't deferred in the
searching on the elements
finally
I thought maybe we could suggest
something from psychology to to these
models to keep keep growing working
differently
based on what we know from psychology so
some things that are not implemented yet
that is actually functioning
have these updating abilities in
intelligent for getting which is real
it's related to
Insight problem solving is when you you
forget something but that it means like
you forget to Prior right you're using a
different prior So you you're able to
yeah let go of biases right
there's also work on thinking
dispositions which could be relevant in
this position additions or sentences
like this
release should always be revised in
response to new information of our
evidence
so this would these will be like
imperative linguistic knowledge which
would have to be added on I don't know
where but
likely would help at work there's a lot
of thinking disposition thinking
dispositions that are relevant to our
successful reasoning and this this is
just one example
yeah the literature and there was a lot
more examples that could be relevant
uh we have in creativity research we
have this generative
phase which is
similar to what the genital models are
doing but we do not have the exploratory
processes going on which is common in
the
creativity research literature
but it's what we do with for instance me
Journey when we're doing better prompts
uh so maybe using these exploratory
processes
uh from the creativity research
we can also automate the exploratory
part of the the creativity processes
that these image generators are getting
to and not just the generative part
and finally I think the embodiments we
don't have robots or anything like that
that do this sort of reasoning so
AI on the computer and also
stuff from active inference which was
not
considered
slightly related to embodiment in the
sense of navigating a world and
predicting the world
that stuff is far from happening in the
traditional elements we have
so yeah there's a lot of stuff said
maybe I hope you guys you guys have some
comments
as I said
uh I haven't been able to talk about
this to
anyone
and
I do think I have some at least some
maybe some relevant stuff that I've
published learned since I'm not famous
and I don't have people to talk to it's
mostly gone unnoticed so thanks for the
space here
thank you awesome presentation all right
Nick it'd be awesome to hear your
introduction and then take it wherever
you'd like to go
sure so first thanks uh Samuel for
interesting talk and I've been really
pleased uh to find your research I guess
um
maybe I'm supposed to say something
about uh who I am where I am so I'm Nick
bird I'm at the Stevens Institute of
Technology in the New York City
metropolitan area uh in a department
that's kind of interdisciplinary so we
have like philosophy and quantitative
social science but also like people
doing like music and visual arts and all
sorts of other things
um I tend to do more of the philosophy
and quantitative social science stuff
um so I'm
kind of also interested in human
reasoning and so much much of the people
I'm reading inciting and drawing on in
my research are a lot of the people that
you saw in the opening slides that we
saw you know people like wayson and
um Kahneman diversky and mercy and
sperber
um and a lot of the other people uh
that were cited um I think Samuel does a
really good job to incorporate the kind
of like
shoulders of giants that we're standing
on in terms of the philosophy of mind
right the the voters and the positions
and the these people
um and
one thing that I think is uh you know on
everybody's mind these days is these
large language models so I'm really glad
to see how this this dual process theory
that was that emerged from research uh
like economy and diverskies on these
these problems like uh you know the
conjunction fallacy problems or the
wayson selection card task or the uh
conjunction fallacy tasks how that has
been applied to models like large
language models and what we can learn
from that and then I think the coolest
thing about the pre-print is
how we could kind of Port back and forth
the learnings from both the computer
science and the the cognitive science to
improve one another right so I think
that one of the neat things about this
preprint that
um Samuel was giving us at the end
is that you know we're kind of taking
what we think is a model of reflective
reasoning
that we like you know we represent
um certain parts of a problem and and
maybe reason more carefully and
effortlessly about them in certain
situations in ways that might help us
and how can we help these large language
models do the same because it does seem
like large language models function
at least the ones that we interact with
online mostly they seem to function
mostly as like a system one or type 1
process they're just kind of like
quickly generating lots of uh text or
imagery or something like that but
they're not necessarily like reflecting
on it and the ways that we would think
that a uh you know a human is capable of
um and they might not even be capable of
like representing things in the same way
that we do
um yeah so I thought that was a really
interesting idea this using Chain of
Thought
and tree of thought models
to kind of create a reflective level or
a reflective system within the models it
seems just like a really valuable idea
and just a really great synthesis of
research and multiple disciplines
something that I think few people are
actually very good at is like
incorporating some of the best insights
from multiple Fields were often pretty
siled in Academia so I just think this
is great work and I hope more people
will
appreciate and pay attention to it and
build on it
so
um one of the things that stood out to
me in this presentation more so than
when I was like reading this 2023
pre-print analytic reasoning for large
language models by Dr Bellini leiche
um that thing that stood out to me is
this idea that like billin Elijah and
Frankish sort of Switched
which of these two types of reasoning
processes are supposed to be context
dependent
or context sensitive or however you
would want to word them
and I started thinking well I wonder if
there's a sense in which both types of
responses or both types of reasoning are
somewhat context dependent and I'll just
say what I mean and then maybe
um Samuel you can kind of
say what you think I should think or or
clarify the view of the predictive and
reflective framework or something so the
thought I was having was
well in a familiar context
these intuitive predictions these type 1
processes are gut response so to speak
those are going to be pretty useful
because they're well trained where we
have a lot of experience that we're
drawing on so like our gut response our
first response is often quite good
it's in these like less familiar
contexts
or maybe similarly familiar but like way
higher Stakes or something but it's in
these other contexts where we might
think oh maybe I should slow down
and make sure I've double checked
whatever my initial impulse is before I
just accept it because there's a lot
writing on this or like I'm just not
used to this this type of problem so I
need to you know I need to slow down
and so there's a sense in which what
what context is doing is not just
um showing up in one or the other type
of reasoning but it's sort of like
determining which type of reasoning
might be best
and at the moment
um but I'm wondering like is that just
totally compatible with what you're
imagining or is that like somehow a
deviation from the framework the the
predictive and reflective framework
yeah thanks for
the thoughts there and compliments and
um thanks for the question as well
so
the reason why I think uh contexts
needs always some sort of type 1 help is
because of the constraints we have
learned from symbolic AI so if I'm
saying that type 2 reasoning
have the same constraints
then it cannot be contextual because it
doesn't know it doesn't work like that
we know that if the sales in contacts it
feels bad
but of course we do need to like when we
have a novel situation
we all often solve this by by context
right so how could this be
and I think it's by the um
interconnection of the power of the
tooth system so
so we always start with a prediction
which in this case would be mistaken and
then we start we have to search for
novel instruments and in this search
uh we make the contextual uh comparisons
so
it can't be that the system two is
making the comparison on its own I think
I think is
uh more likely that when it's a case of
context that stems from
a novel situation and then the two
systems have to figure out together
likely in the sense that I was winning
out here in the end these predictions
that go over the thoughts
the most likely
will
are the ones that will solve these
context issues in the novel problems
yeah I I I'd argue something like that
foreign
that's somewhat helpful so then maybe
what I'm thinking is something along
what the lines you were saying at the
end you were saying how
there's still kind of an opportunity to
understand things like executive
function
[Music]
uh in this framework and I think that's
maybe part of what I'm wondering about
and I'm wondering so I guess I'm
wondering if
yeah if there's more to be said within
this predictive and reflecting framework
about
how each of these two types of processes
get selected or like
what might help the system
that specific point you just remember I
just remember something that that's
related so yeah clearly our working
memory or type 2 reasoning likely does
more than that
it does this but likely more more than
that so
um
there's there's likely also a belief
Bank something like the taking
dispositions
some sort of knowledge bank which is
related to type 2 processing
um so Keith Frankish does this
distinction between
flat out beliefs and
I I'm not remembering the terms but he
has a type 1 belief in type two belief
type 1 believes is that but if you have
but you're not fully confident of it and
the the type 2 believes is the beliefs
you have when you you have a say a very
firm political position and you stated
with obvious war is that you for sure
you believe that
so there's likely to be some sort of
different belief structure as well which
I don't talk about at all in thesis or
the work so I'm not saying obviously
that this is a complete model of
reasoning uh and obviously we need more
to to figure out
how reasoning works so yeah
yeah okay that's that's also helpful
um I'm wondering if Daniel did you want
to weigh in
well I think it's a very interesting
question about which of those modes are
engaged or how they're balanced through
time
and
how does this connect to what's known as
the context window in today's
Transformer type large language models
so how do you map the computational
attributes of large language models
today like architecturally or their Ram
or CPU usage how do you map that onto
for example human cognitive processes do
you think that's useful or there any
insights there
well I'm I'm mostly making a
relation between
uh
predictive processing in genitive models
but I know that's I mean large language
models are not entirely the same as
what's
active influence the same I'm aware of
that but there is some similarity
specifically in regards to regenerative
model parts
so I would I'm not sure I'm not a AI
specialist to
to be sure which details of regenerative
model could be true of the human brain
and I'm most likely betting that uh the
the people who study genitive models in
the brain like the friskins you know
have figured out
something like what our generative
models do
one other thought or Nick do you have it
you want to add there
um just thought of some different ways
whether people have connected it
explicitly to the literature on working
memory in predictive processing I I
think as you pointed out it's definitely
a link that is not highlighted it's one
that we recently heard
um from
uh professors Walker and
uh Manriquez and friston in the recent
livestream 53 that was on like cognitive
paleoanthropology looking at human
working memory but some ways that people
have Incorporated working memory is like
a nested model that carries context at a
deeper time
but that is not necessarily like an
actual mechanism that gives rise to why
type 1 and type 2
are the way they are
um so I thought that was a very
provocative direction to go to move past
the descriptive
and then to
look at the underlying generative model
of why these outcomes are the way they
are even though these cognitive
phenomena are causes of other things
happening
they are also caused by some
influenceable
or contextual or variable aspects
and when we lose that context dependence
of the cognitive systems then they're
totally lifted and disembodied
don't really help
so
by putting the Primacy on that
predictive processing element I think it
opens the door to connecting those areas
Beyond just mentioning the terms in
proximity
but to really
support different epistemologies from
predictive processing as a model or
approach
yeah can you go can you go on that idea
again I'm not sure what you want me to
comment can you summarize that again and
make it a question sure what do you
think the epistemological consequences
are
of taking predictive processing the way
that you have approached it here
versus alternative or or prior
approaches to cognitive Sciences
okay but what do you mean by
systemological
Advance with this Theory
um how it influences our our
understanding of how we know or seek or
practice or do or decide
perfect okay so let me let me think
about this
um
yeah I think one of the best uh
what this helps with most is explaining
dual process Theory because dual process
theory is in bad shape in terms of
Concepts uh in terms of theory and
formulation
uh
people have no idea
what these these systems refer to in the
mind brain uh we often have
you know different intuitions into this
and basically basically what I most
think this work is relevant for is for
saving dual process Theory from
criticism
which has been happening in Psychology
so people are like it seems like you're
talking about the left and right brain
right something like that something
that we don't know for sure what these
two systems are right
um
so this is a good way forward I think uh
for for dual process Theory and as
a sad little processity does have
some value in itself
uh so
yeah saving the process Theory I think
it's a good
direction for
so this is this model but also if we if
we think about
the
advantages of it
would be something like for instance
it could have helped us had the idea
of using chain of thoughts or
or tree of thoughts had anyone read this
before so
it can help us make these these sources
of predictions that we shouldn't have
some sort of Serial reasoning coupled to
the genitive models so yeah I think you
can help us think on
further on on AI if we
uh AI like like like Nicholas saying to
like incorporating more stuff in
Psychology than we know but it's
certainly missing here but
here we have a direction of what we
should incorporate and so on yeah but
yeah I'm also unaware of the working
memory research from predictive
processing you mentioned and if you want
to go back to that and explain me some
more of that I'd be happy to hear
thanks
yeah sure so not that this is the most
effective way to implement a memory
system but at least that this provides
uh analytical method for measuring or
describing them if one we're going to
have the five digit number you can
imagine a a nested model where the
lowest level is the ones place and it's
nested within a decision tree of tens
places and hundreds and so on
and then there's some
seek or access
policy or strategy
that helps speak the number in reverse
and some cognitive or computational
limitation is just
how well that cognitive agent can
perform on that
test again that doesn't mean that's the
mechanism that's being used but that
would be a way to use a nested
generative model
to encode like multiple levels of
spatial or temporal variability but
context becomes an issue because you're
basically just expanding the the
possibility space
looking for sparser and sparse or
associations so if you don't have a good
compositionality
or really well-definable
well-articulated causal process
then you're just building these all by
all models that you're going to be
searching through in the dark
yeah one final and a comment on that is
that well
it's not clear that the best way to
reason will be the way humans reason
right so we might eventually have a
different way of implementing a working
memory on an llm which would be more
effective than ours
there's also a lot to the other side
there's also the point that
it seems that the limited capacity we
have on working memory maybe it's not
just a lack of power maybe it's
necessary so we kind of like don't lose
our minds in the sense that we have a
limited space to search
and then we're able to search the disc
limited space and if it was too uh if
you have if we had too much space to
search because we had a super super
working memory then we wouldn't be able
to finish the tasks in time so maybe
this is like a physical
good uh barrier that's something that
helps
and it's interesting that what I find
interesting
is that
okay the act the AI may find a lot a lot
of different better ways to implement
worth memory but it's interesting that
they implemented a virtual memory
or a search agents which was very very
like the way I described in the thesis
that was the
well they found amazing
as you were saying there's there's very
ways Implement they worked in memory but
they did it in a very similar similar
way in the sense of searching the space
after the generative model
has offered a solution right so I don't
know maybe that's a a good
a good uh indication that this is on the
right track but it also may just simply
be a simple way they found to
to solve the problem and it was just by
coincidence similar to this so yeah
maybe the correct way or the way the
brain does may also be different we
don't know right all we have it was the
The Limited evidence I I
offered a bit more obviously and uh some
constraints we know on AI and
information processing and you have to
figure it out and I think that this
implementation stuff we're asking is
mostly
mostly due to the AI people to find out
or the the math paperwork assistance to
figure out
Nick do you want to comment or a
question or I'll ask one from the chat
yeah so I just have a kind of a bigger
picture question that kind of gets us
into the realm of these chat Bots
um right so you in this pre-print and
um in this talk have like given us a
variety of different tasks in the
heuristics and biases literature the the
conjunction fallacy to uh task the Linda
problem some people call it
um or these cognitive reflection test
questions and um you know there's a
there's like a paper in the fall that
showed that a preprint uh in the fall
that last fall that show 2022 that
showed
GPT 3 and 3.5 and even the earlier
versions like showed a lot of the
human-like
faulty intuitions and I can basically
fell for the lure pretty often
sometimes like most of the time it was
falling for the lure but then as soon as
chat or gpt4 uh was was available to be
studied and used on these models it was
like performing basically near perfect
and when it did get the incorrect
response it wasn't necessarily the lure
it was just like some other General type
of error it was making like
misinterpreting the question altogether
or something
and it seems like the predict the
predicting predictive and reflecting
model
framework
could have at least two different ways
of explaining this like one is like uh
what happened is they changed the AIS
like type 1 thinking or whatever so that
like it could uh respond intuitively to
all uh to all these but intuitively and
correctly so it didn't need to reflect
or it could be that like they somehow
created this like reflective type system
with either like you know a Chain of
Thought or a tree of thought or some
other type of system that helps it
actually engage in reflection on these
these tasks or whatever the analog of
reflection would be for a chat bot
um and so I'm wondering like if you have
thoughts on this like as you've been
thinking about this or talking to anyone
about this like which how do you think
they did this obviously we have to
speculate because a lot of the data is
proprietary but I'm just curious to get
your thoughts
yeah that's an awesome question yeah I
actually forgot to mention this on the
presentation that the uh
the the biases they make on the recent
test last year were exactly the ones the
the humans made so if we if we uh said
it's um
dual process real it would give exactly
our mistakes that's that's so amazing
I'm not certain why that happened but it
did
and
um
how they fixed this
so yeah I do think that they
trained the model on these tasks because
people were able to like
uh get similar
similar issues by changing the questions
a little bit so I think they like
cheated on that
in the sense that they trained on
unknown problems
but that's not true of new problems if
you should give it some different
formulation and feed it to I don't know
3.5 new version
it's still it's still failing but
uh the people on open AI they they are
aware of this chain of thoughts research
they are aware of this tree of thought
research
but I don't think they want to
Depend and rely on these external agents
so they recently uh released a report
where they are trying to
reinforce intermediate steps of
reasoning on gpc4 so they try to
simulate
internally what the the chain of
thoughts reasoning is doing externally
by
reinforcing the intermediate
intermediate steps of reasoning so that
it stops feeling composition helping so
on okay
yeah I'll add a thought on that I was
reminded by Daniel Dennis
framework or model In Darwin's dangerous
idea of cranes and Sky Hooks and so some
building is built and then the question
is like was it built with cranes or with
top-down hung Sky hooks that just sort
of descend from nowhere to hold
everything up while it's all being built
and it's like well no it's with cranes
and then if you need a big crane you can
use a smaller crane to assemble a crane
so that's kind of a bottom-up
constructive metaphor whereas the sky
hook is like the top down
compositionality and that's when you get
to certain level of sophistication for a
cognitive system it can make the
blueprint or the plan
like maybe what we would associate with
the expected free energy calculation not
just the variational free energy
calculation so at some point when a plan
can be made it requires a strategy
between type 1 and type 2 switching and
probably other switches too
um and so that crane approach
you need a lot of compute
to do a bottom up so even though it's
kind of weird to think about it's almost
like the current large models are very
bottom up because they're very bottom up
from syntax and they don't have
um what you refer to as imperative
linguistic knowledge which can be
normative as well as a heuristic for
knowledge and that's potentially a small
model
but it contains wisdom that's explicit
and practices and um stances or or
dispositions as you described and so
it's kind of like
it's not a denial of embodiments to also
clarify what this sky hook
ability is and it's type 2 like
so I think
[Music]
um
I guess what do you think about that or
how do you connect this to anything in
that area
yeah
but if you do the summary in the
question again because although I didn't
track some of what you mean I'm not sure
which ones made to comment on that
do you think that the uh landscape of
large and small models would be
different if people took on board some
of the
the features you described like
imperative linguistic knowledge
seriously into construction of models
so let me just see if this is something
you're asking so they're they're doing
small models now for phones and open
source models performance and they have
the issue of not being able to scale up
right because if you scale up too much
then you can't run the form
uh so you're asking if we can Implement
something
like uh tree of thoughts to
to have these small smaller models
yes
yes are you sure are you just saying
okay go for that that's an example of
what it would mean to re-understand like
where do we need an API call to a cloud
Center or where could some context be
locally computed with much more of a
type one what are some type 2 problems
that we might be able to type one or way
out of what are some type 1 areas where
things are not working and a type 2
um description might be advantageous
yeah yeah I think they're they're
getting on to that and they're they're
being able to make these smaller smaller
models precisely because of these sorts
of um
discoveries they made on chain of
thoughts right there's also stuff about
being able to train on specific data I
read one
it's called textbooks are all you need
the the training smaller smaller models
on the textbooks
and they're doing better so yeah there's
there are differences in the training
oh
training smaller models and different
data but there's also this the
possibility of
making them more reliable based on
what I'm calling T2 agents or train of
thoughts stuff like that and again we
don't know if that's all we can do
externally but I would argue that we we
would need necessarily some sort of
external mechanism coupled to any large
language model for the best results
because of the differences in
representations mainly because of this
right unless the large language model
somehow
uh makes a symbolic representation
emerge from its processes it's likely
that it has done so but unless it's it
does so
and it uses that reliably because they
may even have generated some sort of
symbolic process internally but doesn't
always use that or doesn't know when to
use that so
yeah most likely we're going to need
something external to the language model
and um
yeah this this is some
Clues to to how to implement it to
implement that and also
I think in our brain it's kind of
external not only in the sense of our
minds but also in the brain since it's a
recent step in evolution
uh we don't see I don't know
okay
and blizzards
reasoning in type 2 manner right
uh we do see chimpanzees originally in
type 2 manners but not as much as we do
so it's very human-like reasoning uh
it's just that
going back to the context problem
animals do solve contextual problems
that that's why they can they can live
right so the issue is not actually the
context there it's more like uh
so
based on reasoning capacity in that
boost on missing capacity may be related
to the preference the prefrontal cortex
as we know and so of course the prefold
to the prefrontal cortex is also a
network it's not a Serial turing machine
but
if uh it's it's there's somewhere it's
implementing
a Serial machine or a symbolic classic
AI machine or symbolic reasoning or
something like that
most likely it would be the prefrontal
cortex which is
kind of like a distinct addiction an
addition to the brain and maybe
something related to language is also
which is also it's uh distinct
a new uh
addition to the brain
so yeah and also I'm very convinced by
the solar Indonesian argument in 3dh
that
okay you're gonna need symbolic
processing anyway right either the model
is gonna generate decimal processing or
you're going to have to feed it for any
because or else you're going to have the
whole destination or mistakes and
reasoning because of the nature of
because of the nature of
distributed representations right it's
it's uncertain in ambiguous by Nature
that's why I'm not entirely convinced
that only probabilistic representations
would be enough to
solve continuation issues
awesome Nick do you have any other
questions or areas you want to mention
or ask
I think um I think those were my main
questions
um I don't know if there's anything in
the chat that you wanted to touch on
before we go I know we're maybe over
time
I'll go with one from the chat and then
we can have any closing thoughts so glia
maximilisk glia maximalist asks are you
familiar with visual Pathways in the
human brain specifically the dorsal wear
and ventral what Pathways do you think
this maps onto the two systems you
describe for problem solving
okay yeah so like I said into in 2008
Evans
tried to accomplish that unifying vision
of due process Theory
but
I'm not very
convinced by that I mean he he also said
well we can't do this as of yet but I I
do think it's possible as I said on the
presentation
I just don't know how to do it uh how to
have a um
convincing
Theory of Everything
of dual process theory in the brain
uh this it does go on to other regions
like you have automatic motor responses
and controlled motor responses
uh
and and like you said there's a
different different Pathways in
reasoning uh in figuring out stuff and
the uh visual field so
yeah maybe the what would be related to
something and would wear to another
most likely the what would be
would be
tapping on to type 2 processing
but I'm not sure how the where it would
be tapping on that but yeah as I'm
trying to make the point if we extend it
to the whole brain it we lose what we
we've learned we're not sure about that
applies
foreign
well Nick any penultimate last words
uh you're muted
oh wait unmute and then continue
sorry about that
um thanks uh thanks to both of you
uh Dr Bellini latte and uh Daniel for
coordinating this and I'm really just
glad to have found uh the research and
to discuss it and connect and uh looking
forward to further conversations to be
honest
awesome
Sam any closing thoughts
yeah I'm just sad I couldn't go much uh
beyond what I said in the presentation
yeah most of the stuff you you guys
asked uh I'm not sure I have good
answers for that
basically what I've done is all I know
and I'm not sure
classical uh
on the future with this and maybe
someone in the artist audience will do
so I hope that that helps
great I hope so too
all right until next time thank you
bye